<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<elsevier name="abstract" ndocs="50">
<article ocid="1">
	<artid>782443af3e715e66dbf4a0d1f967ad9c</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000473</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00047-3</doi>
	<title>Response of the Dominant Alga Fucus gardneri (Silva) (Phaeophyceae) to the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill and Clean-up </title>
	<abstract>The Coastal Habitat Injury Assessment Study was initiated to assess injury to and recovery of intertidal habitats affected by the Exxon Valdez oil spill, 1989, and subsequent clean-up. The spill area was divided into three major regions: Prince William Sound (PWS), Cook Inlet-Kenai (CIK) and Kodiak–Alaska Peninsula (KAP) and distinct habitat types within the area. The dominant intertidal macrophyte, Fucus gardneri, was impacted over the entire area of the spill, although observed differences varied across regions, habitats, and tidal heights. Generally F. gardneri biomass and percent cover were reduced in most habitats. However, at the low intertidal in CIK sheltered rocky habitat, the F. gardneri population was enhanced at the expense of annuals. Thalli of F. gardneri at oiled sites were not as reproductively competent as those at reference sites. Population structures were also altered. A greater proportion of adult F. gardneri thalli had attached epiphytes in oiled sites. Additional data collected during 1992–1994, indicate varying rates of recovery for F. gardneri populations.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="2">
	<artid>bb147b39e9495a4356becf9ca912f370</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X0000045X</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00045-X</doi>
	<title>Standardization of the Preparation and Quantitation of Water-accommodated Fractions of Petroleum for Toxicity Testing </title>
	<abstract>Oil spill response can be highly affected by the perceived costs and benefits of a particular countermeasure. Responders’ perceptions of these can be influenced by the way in which scientific data are collected and presented. To date, a large amount of information has been generated on the aquatic toxicity of oil, dispersants and dispersed oil. Unfortunately, much of these data are not comparable because of differing toxicological and analytical methods used, as well as frequent lack of analytical verification of exposures. Recently, a group of federal, state, academic and industry representatives from North America and Europe have been working toward standardizing both biological and analytical methods used to produce acute toxicity estimates of complex mixtures such as oil, dispersants and dispersed oil. This standardization provides guidelines for future investigations to be conducted in a sufficiently rigourous manner that both inter- and intra-laboratory datasets will be comparable, thus providing a more coherent and robust database from which to derive response guidance.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="3">
	<artid>4dd8f9de478712e6f1daf80df919c45b</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000424</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00042-4</doi>
	<title>Hydrocarbons in Coastal Sediments of Patagonia, Argentina: Levels and Probable Sources </title>
	<abstract>Intertidal superficial sediment from the Patagonian coastal zone were analysed to determine the concentration and probable source of aromatic and aliphatic hydrocarbons. Concentrations of aromatic and aliphatic hydrocarbons ranged from non-detected to 737.6 μg/g and non-detected to 1304.7 μg/g of dry sediment, respectively. High concentrations were observed in San Jorge Gulf, where the main economic activities are based on crude oil production. The highest aromatic and aliphatic hydrocarbon concentrations were present at Faro Aristizábal, 200 km away from oil charging areas. As suspected, hydrocarbon levels in harbour areas were generally more important than at nearby zones. Lower or non-detected hydrocarbon levels were recorded at locations with low or non-anthropogenic activity. Alkane distribution indices and hydrocarbon distribution patterns were used to identify natural and anthropogenic inputs. The results showed recent crude oil inputs and contribution from remaining weathered residues at various locations, whereas biogenic compounds or biogenic in combination with anthropogenic hydrocarbons predominated in others.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="4">
	<artid>6eff7cb04a123f3a2ad10f8cb393b4d6</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000448</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00044-8</doi>
	<title>The Distribution of Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons in Surficial Sediments of Sydney Harbour, Australia </title>
	<abstract>Surface sediment was collected from 124 sites in Sydney Harbour and analysed for the 16 polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) listed as priority pollutants by the US EPA, as well as 2-methylnaphthalene. PAH concentrations varied widely, from &lt;100 to 380 000 &lt;1 K)&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: -5px; vertical-align: middle&quot; title=&quot;Full-size image (&lt;1 K)&quot; src=&quot;/sd/grey_pxl.gif&quot; data-inlimgeid=&quot;1-s2.0-S0025326X00000448-si1.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;1 K)&quot; title=&quot;Full-size image (&lt;1 K)&quot; src=&quot;http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0025326X00000448-si1.gif&quot;&gt;g kg−1 of total PAH. The spatial distribution of PAHs suggested that they derive predominantly from urban run-off. However, discrete point sources of PAH appear to exist at several sites. The relative abundance of individual PAH compounds was remarkably consistent throughout the harbour and indicated that high temperature combustion processes are the predominant source of PAH contamination in Sydney Harbour. Comparison with numerical effects-based sediment quality guidelines derived in the US indicated that most of the sites studied in Sydney Harbour (89%) have levels of PAH which are predicted to either occasionally or frequently result in adverse biological effects.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="5">
	<artid>b0aab57731a2192846eea640a717aaf2</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000461</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00046-1</doi>
	<title>Amphipods are Good Bioindicators of the Impact of Oil Spills on Soft-Bottom Macrobenthic Communities </title>
	<abstract>The Amoco Cadiz oil spill in 1978, and the Aegean Sea oil spill in 1992, affected soft-bottom communities, respectively from the Bay of Morlaix (western English Channel) and from the Rı́a de Ares and Betanzos in the north-western Iberian peninsula. These infralittoral communities on muddy fine sand showed similar species composition and structure and occurred in similar hydro-climatic conditions. The effects of the spills were identical in both areas with the disappearance of the amphipods especially those from the amphipod genus Ampelisca with a very low colonization of these species during the four years after the spill. The recovery rate of the amphipods was slow but progressive. In such communities no proliferation of opportunistics was observed after the stress. In the sites, where polychaetes dominated before the spill, they remained dominant, whereas other sites showed very low total abundances during the two years after the spill due to the absence of compensation for the disappearance of these crustaceans. In fact, there was a very low impact of the spill on polychaetes, but a high one on amphipods. In the future, it is suggested to focus monitoring after a spill only on a single amphipod group proposed as a bioindicator for detecting the impact of pollution. A polychaete/amphipod ratio is proposed to reflect temporal change of soft-bottom communities analogous to the nematode/copepod previously suggested for the meiobenthos. Detailed knowledge of the qualitative and quantitative structure of a benthic community is still needed in order to identify very precisely the effect of a pollution event.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="6">
	<artid>2184f85f256658df6181a6b765eaf99b</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000503</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00050-3</doi>
	<title>Entanglement of Pinnipeds in Synthetic Materials at South-east Farallon Island, California, 1976–1998 </title>
	<abstract>Entanglement records of hauled out pinnipeds are useful for monitoring trends in impacts of synthetic materials, a principal contaminant, upon pinniped populations. This report documents entanglement of five species (California Sea Lions, Northern Elephant Seals, Steller Sea Lions, Pacific Harbor Seals, and Northern Fur Seals) at South-east Farallon Island (SEFI), an island in Northern California, 1976–1998, when a total of 914 pinnipeds were observed entangled in or with body constrictions from synthetic material. There was a significant decrease in entangled Northern Elephant Seals over the study period. Of the 27 Steller Sea Lions observed entangled, 37% were adult Steller Sea Lions entangled in salmon fishing gear. This report highlights an ongoing problem of entanglement of pinnipeds in synthetic materials in Northern California.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="7">
	<artid>79f22da261802b9a096ea0c781ce22eb</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000485</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00048-5</doi>
	<title>Benthic Foraminiferal Tolerance to Tri-n-Butyltin (TBT) Pollution in an Experimental Mesocosm </title>
	<abstract>Tri-n-butyltin (TBT) has been used in the marine environment as a toxic agent in antifouling paints, but unfortunately it also has negative effects on non-target organisms in the environment. In this study, intact coastal sediment was exposed for seven months to three levels of TBT corresponding to nominal additions of 0.00, 0.02 and 2.00 nmol TBT per g dry sediment. This paper presents the first attempt to find out how living benthic foraminifera respond to TBT. Increased foraminiferal abundance in the 0.02 nmol mesocosm could be an effect of decreased predation (competition), since other representatives of meiofauna and macrofauna tended to be less tolerant to TBT. Increasing toxicity in the most contaminated mesocosm group (2.00 nmol) resulted in a less abundant foraminiferal population suggesting that TBT affects the foraminiferal community.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="8">
	<artid>e54c0cae56357e82111f5e2b1c91a762</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000436</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00043-6</doi>
	<title>Copper Effects on Potential Sediment Test Organisms: the Importance of Appropriate Sensitivity </title>
	<abstract>This article provides a review of available information on the sensitivities to copper of marine and estuarine organisms, primarily those that might be suitable for use in sediment toxicity tests, including temperate and tropical species. This review was necessitated by a need to identify a suitably sensitive test species for a specific study when preliminary testing showed that the original species selected was insensitive to copper. This example illustrates the importance of ensuring that the relative sensitivity of test species to the contaminant(s) of interest is evaluated as part of test species selection.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="9">
	<artid>b847ee10b86ba38b938129f8ed06a3f5</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000552</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00055-2</doi>
	<title>Effects of Residual Exxon Valdez Oil on Intertidal Protothaca staminea: Mortality, Growth, and Bioaccumulation of Hydrocarbons in Transplanted Clams </title>
	<abstract>Effects of residual Exxon Valdez oil on the intertidal clam, Protothaca staminea, were studied using reciprocal experimental transplants of clams between unoiled and oiled sites. Individually tagged clams were transplanted in 1994 and collected in 1995 and 1996. Mortality, growth, and tissue chemistry data were collected from reference unoiled and oiled clams, clams transplanted from an oiled to unoiled site, and clams moved from an unoiled to oiled site. Greatest mortality occurred in clams originating from the oiled site. Best growth occurred in clams moved from the oiled site to the unoiled area. Largest tissue burdens of hydrocarbons occurred in oiled site clams. There was indication of depuration of hydrocarbons when oiled site clams were transplanted to the unoiled site. Clams transplanted from the unoiled site to oiled site accumulated hydrocarbons after one year. Our results indicate that residual oil, 5–6 years following the EV oil spill, affected survival and growth rates of clams.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="10">
	<artid>55ca76d1f727f9b403b59b5ff9d6d0db</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000588</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00058-8</doi>
	<title>The Role of Burrows of the SW Atlantic Intertidal Crab Chasmagnathus granulata in Trapping Debris </title>
	<abstract>The burrowing crab Chasmagnathus granulata is the most abundant macroinvertebrate on intertidal mudflats and salt marshes of the South Western Atlantic. This species excavates and maintains large semi permanent open burrows with a mouth opening that may reach 20 cm in diameter and a volume of up to 2 l. Areas populated by crabs retain a significantly larger amount of debris (mainly plastics) on the surface and have larger amounts of buried debris in the sediment than areas without crabs. Field experiments showed that due to their hydrodynamic characteristics, burrows in the mudflats work as passive traps for debris enhancing their retention. Given the extensive intertidal area inhabited by this species in SW Atlantic estuaries, crab bed areas should be considered as large areas that retain debris burying it in the soft bottom environment.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="11">
	<artid>a53d66fa34090413fc37d6f45d819ba9</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000564</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00056-4</doi>
	<title>Aerial Surveillance of Operational Oil Pollution in Belgium’s Maritime Zone of Interest </title>
	<abstract>Belgium’s Maritime Zone of Interest (BMZI), including the Belgian Territorial Sea, Belgian Continental Shelf, and Bonn Agreement Zone of Multilateral Responsibility, were regularly surveyed by remote-sensing aircraft for the presence of operational oil spills between 1991 and 1995. Simultaneously wind speed and direction were recorded; wave height was obtained from the literature. In total, 228 spills of various sizes, volumes and origins were analysed by means of univariate statistical analysis. We documented that the observed oil spills were generally elongate, narrow and thin, that spill dimensions were interrelated, and that wind speed and wave height affected these dimensions. A major fraction of the total variation however could be attributed to slick thickness. Spills found outside the Traffic Separation Scheme (TSS) tended to be smaller in surface area but showed no significant difference in average volume. Thus, the source of the spill more so than the hydrodynamics of the sea determined the characteristics of the spill. Given the impact of oil spills on marine life, continuous attention should be paid to monitoring and pollution control measures in the BMZI.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="12">
	<artid>7ad20a9aab0bf601150c196c93d0b861</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000680</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00068-0</doi>
	<title>Variability of Trace-Metal Concentrations Within and Between Colonies of Pocillopora damicornis </title>
	<abstract>Variations of cadmium, lead, copper, nickel and chromium concentrations in tissues and skeletons of the scleractinian coral Pocillopora damicornis were measured to provide information for designing bio-assay surveys involving this organism. Intra-colony variations were measured using multiple portions from individual colonies, and inter-colony variations were measured using single portions from different colonies of a coral community. We found that specific metals partitioned differently into tissue and skeletal parts, possibly because selectivity for each metal differed due to biochemical utility or toxicity. Intra-colony variations in metal concentrations were inconsistent, and skewed distributions of tissue-metal concentrations were sometimes observed. Overall, the application of tissues for heavy-metal bio-assays is compromised by inconsistent intra-colony variation, and the substantial material needed to represent tissue-biomass. In contrast, small replicate samples of skeleton can be collected from a colony, allowing representation of intra-colony metal variation with minimal damage to the organism.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="13">
	<artid>09d5d668165bb87bf7a87160fceba139</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000655</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00065-5</doi>
	<title>Early Contamination by Heavy Metals of the Guadalquivir Estuary After the Aznalcóllar Mining Spill (SW Spain) </title>
	<abstract>The Guadalquivir estuary was impacted by the accidental release of 5 million cubic meters of acid waste from the processing of pyrite ore (25 April 1998). The waste entered ecologically sensitive and protected areas such as the National Park of Doñana. Here are presented the results obtained from a time sequence of different sampling sites in the estuary and in the surrounding areas from May to September 1998. Water, suspended solids and sediments were analysed for six different metals (Fe, Mn, Zn, Cd, Pb, Cu). Also, the concentration of the metals in the different geochemical sediment fractions was determined as a means of assessing bioavailability. The results obtained during the first weeks after the incident show high concentrations of Zn. At the end of June a 10 000 m3 temporary water-treatment plant was constructed on site for depuration of the toxic waters. The results obtained in August and September show a decrease in the metal concentrations measured in the estuary. Only concentrations of Zn were higher than sediment quality values proposed by various authors.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="14">
	<artid>ad76981ab4717343154656378a4ccfaa</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000667</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00066-7</doi>
	<title>The Consequences of the Oder Flood in 1997 on the Distribution of Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons (PAHs) in the Oder River Estuary </title>
	<abstract>Changes in the levels and spatial distribution of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) as a consequence of the Oder flood in the summer of 1997 were investigated in surface water samples and fluffy layer material from the Oder Lagoon and the Pomeranian Bight. The measurements of the contaminants were complemented by satellite data to describe the spreading of the Oder flood discharge including the distribution of the particulate material. During the flood elevated levels of PAHs were discussed in the surface water and fluffy layer material of the Oder River Estuary in comparison to the average values in this region. These increased concentrations were attributed to flooding of municipal and industrial waste disposal areas in the drainage area of the Oder River. The meteorological conditions during the sampling period were characterized by predominant easterly winds, which guided the river plume along the German coast into the Arkona Sea, as verified by satellite observations. The highest concentrations of PAHs were observed near the mouth of the Swina and along the main direction of the river plume. Elevated concentrations of PAHs were also found in fluffy layer samples taken from the Oder Lagoon in late August. As derived from satellite data the eastern and the western parts of the lagoon differed in their SPM load during the entire flood period. The eastern part was covered by Oder water, while the western part contained a mixture of Oder Lagoon water. The highest concentrations of PAHs were not observed in the western part with the highest suspended matter values, but in the eastern part where the flood water entered the lagoon. Despite the significantly increased PAH levels measured during the flood, all measured concentrations were below the values that are considered to pose a risk to the ecosystem.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="15">
	<artid>174c19ea9a2815752c5eace813a5bf87</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000618</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00061-8</doi>
	<title>A Marine Biotic Index to Establish the Ecological Quality of Soft-Bottom Benthos Within European Estuarine and Coastal Environments </title>
	<abstract>In this paper, a marine Biotic Index (BI) for soft-bottom benthos of European estuarine and coastal environments is proposed. This is derived from the proportions of individual abundance in five ecological groups, which are related to the degree of sensitivity/tolerance to an environmental stress gradient. The main difference with previously published indices is the use of a simple formula that produces a continuous Biotic Coefficient (BC) – which makes it more suitable for statistical analysis, in opposition with previous discreet biotic indices – not affected by subjectivity. Relationships between this coefficient and a complementary BI with several environmental variables are discussed. Finally, a validation of the proposed index is made with data from systems affected by recent human disturbances, showing that different anthropogenic changes in the environment can be detected through the use of this BI.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="16">
	<artid>27f67bff02eccac1f73969b7e85fd084</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000643</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00064-3</doi>
	<title>Bleaching Damage and Recovery Potential of Maldivian Coral Reefs </title>
	<abstract>Same-site comparisons of Maldive–Chagos reefs in the 1990s with studies before 1980 have found large losses in coral cover that were probably associated with warm El Niño events. To determine the spatial extent of this damage and potential for recovery I surveyed benthic cover, hard coral communities, and coral recruitment in previously unsurveyed sites in three reef atolls of the central Maldives in 1999, one year after the warmest recorded El Niño event of 1997–1998. Coral cover was the lowest recorded for this region, at 8%, and evidence for the local extirpation of species was found. Most reefs are presently dominated by coralline and turf algae (68%) with erect fleshy algae and sponge being higher than previously reported on Maldivian reefs. Branching coral species appeared most affected and the dominant coral genera in 1998 were massive Porites and Astreopora, whereas the original community was dominated by Acropora. Coral recruits were sufficiently abundant, at 29 ind/m2, to insure recovery of coral cover, but the most common recruits were in genera previously reported as subordinate genera, such as Pavona (11.7 ind/m2) and Coscinarea (4.4 ind/m2), whereas the previously dominant branching and encrusting species (Acropora, Montipora and Pocillopora) had recruit densities less than 0.65 ind/m2. Unless there is significant compensation in growth and mortality there may be future changes in coral species composition and benthic cover of these reefs.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="17">
	<artid>b005f5af7fdc7057b15ba2619b650f57</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000679</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00067-9</doi>
	<title>Bioerosion of Live Massive Corals and Branching Coral Rubble on Indonesian Coral Reefs </title>
	<abstract>The degree of bioerosion of live massive corals and rubble from branching corals were measured on nine reefs from two regions of Indonesia: the Java Sea and Ambon. Bioerosion in massive corals was measured by collecting live corals, cutting and X-raying slabs, and measuring the cross-sectional area removed from each slab by the various bioeroding organisms. A technique analysing branching coral rubble was developed and similarly used to evaluate the degree of bioerosion on the reefs. This rubble technique has potential advantages over the massive coral technique since it does not require the expense and technical expertise of making and analysing X-rays, nor does it require the destruction of living coral heads. The effectiveness of this rubble technique is evaluated here. Levels of bioerosion in massive coral heads and rubble from branching corals are each compared with environmental variables and health parameters of the nine reefs. Overall, both techniques showed that bioerosion levels were positively correlated with environmental variables indicative of eutrophication. Bioerosion of live massive corals and of branching coral rubble were positively correlated. At the Ambon sites, where the eutrophication levels differ only slightly compared to the Java sites, bioerosion in coral rubble was a more sensitive indicator of eutrophication stress than bioerosion measured from massive coral heads. The rubble technique we outline is a useful rapid reef assessment technique that could be a valuable contribution to the `reef survey toolbox&apos;.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="18">
	<artid>3115830a90c2531bf5c34ca463de9222</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X0000076X</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00076-X</doi>
	<title>Concentration of Chlorinated Hydrocarbons and Heavy Metals in Alaska Arctic Marine Mammals </title>
	<abstract>Over the last decade, a baseline database on anthropogenic contaminants in Alaska marine mammals has been developing through the efforts of several independent investigations as well as larger research programs. Although still somewhat limited in scope, the largest amount of data exists for polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs), DDT, mercury, and cadmium in walrus, beluga whale, bowhead whale, and ringed seal. Because of their relatively large contribution to the total chlorinated hydrocarbon levels in Arctic species, chlordane and toxaphene are two pesticides that are also gaining attention. Comparison of the Alaska database with the results of studies conducted in Canada and Greenland, indicates that patterns of many accumulative substances are quite similar in species that occur across the North American Arctic.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="19">
	<artid>5fe483395cbfb25bf0c7e4f21b55091e</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000692</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00069-2</doi>
	<title>The Use of Cholinesterase Activity in Flounder (Platichthys flesus) Muscle Tissue as a Biomarker of Neurotoxic Contamination in UK Estuaries </title>
	<abstract>This study investigated the occurrence and levels of neurotoxic contamination in UK estuaries by the determination of cholinesterase (ChE) activity in the muscle of the flounder (Platichthys flesus). Samples were obtained from 16 sites in the estuaries of the rivers Humber, Mersey, Tamar, Tees and Tyne. ChE activity levels were compared to those at a reference site- the River Alde, Suffolk. Twelve sites exhibited significantly (p&lt;0.05) reduced ChE activity. The Tyne estuary showed a strong gradient of effect that suggested a source of neurotoxic-contamination upstream of the sampled sites. Representative water samples from several of the estuaries were analysed for the presence of 32 organophosphate (OP) and 20 carbamate (C) pesticides from which residues of nine OPs and six Cs were detected. Correlation analysis of ChE activity with gender, size, GSI, HSI and condition factor suggested that these variables did not influence neural activity in this study. It was concluded that the reduction in ChE activity was contaminant mediated and that OP and C pesticides were probable contributors. Influences on ChE activity, higher order implications and its use as a monitoring tool, including reactivation techniques, are discussed.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="20">
	<artid>26a95f398e33cf5a777c462cbff69b0f</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000709</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00070-9</doi>
	<title>The Effects of a Small Sewage Outfall on an Algal Epifaunal Community at Macquarie Island (sub-Antarctic): A Drop in the Southern Ocean? </title>
	<abstract>Macquarie Island, in the sub-Antarctic, is the location of one of four permanently staffed bases operated by the Australian Antarctic Division. As part of a wider programme investigating the effects of human presence on Antarctic and sub-Antarctic ecosystems, this study evaluated the impact of the small sewage outfall at Macquarie Island on the epifauna living within turfs of the intertidal red alga Chaetangium fastigiatum. Sampling was conducted during early December (austral summer) in both 1996 and 1997 at six sites, two sites within each of three adjacent bays. The site closest to the outfall was 3 m from the point of discharge. Data analyses at the population and community levels failed to demonstrate a significant effect of the outfall. Small scale spatial patterns, probably related to wave exposure, and inter-annual variation in recruitment, are suggested as the main causes of variation in patterns of epifaunal dominance during the study.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="21">
	<artid>5f4c48e3c8ac01e2047d118555f0bc6d</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000771</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00077-1</doi>
	<title>Distribution of Enteric Bacteria in Antarctic Seawater Surrounding the Dumont d’Urville Permanent Station (Adélie Land) </title>
	<abstract>The survival of human enteric bacteria in the aquatic environment has attracted much interest in view of its public health significance. Untreated sewage has been released from Dumont d&apos;Urville station, Antarctica, into the Southern Ocean for several years. The spatial distribution of faecal bacteria indicators was investigated in summer ice-free seawater near the French Base station of the Adélie land area. A complementary seasonal survey of the occurrence of faecal coliform bacteria was conducted in seawater under the winter sea ice in a specific station. Relatively high bacterial densities (maximum 103 CFU 100 ml−1) were found in seawater surrounding the sewage outfall. However, the contamination decreased rapidly with increasing distance from the outfall. In all samples collected further than 2 km, the bacterial indicators were absent or present in very small numbers. Faecal coliforms were not detected in samples collected at pristine sites. Despite these relatively low contamination levels, faecal bacteria were always detected in the vicinity of the sewage outfall during the seasonal survey conducted in ice and under-ice seawater.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="22">
	<artid>b3a7997d824209e3a3dfc578983472a3</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000746</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00074-6</doi>
	<title>Relationship Between Oil Exposure and Reproductive Parameters in Fish Collected Following the Exxon Valdez Oil Spill </title>
	<abstract>Following the Exxon Valdez oil spill (EVOS) in 1989, the effect of oil exposure on reproductive parameters was investigated in wild populations of female dolly varden, yellowfin sole, and pollock. Exposure to oil was the highest in the first year of sampling and decreased in the subsequent years of sampling. Both positive and negative correlations between reproductive parameters and indices of exposure were detected in varying degrees for all three species. Reproductive parameters were not measured in the first year of sampling. For those parameters found to be significantly correlated to oil exposure, an exponential regression function was used to project reproductive parameters of fish sampled in the first year of the spill. A higher proportion of dolly varden sampled in 1989 were projected to have depressed plasma estradiol-17β compared to the fish sampled in 1990.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="23">
	<artid>ea7a12587bd31104ce36557da5e2bfc4</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000837</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00083-7</doi>
	<title>Infaunal Assemblages on Constructed Intertidal Mudflats at Jonesport, Maine (USA) </title>
	<abstract>Dredged materials have been used to construct two mudflats near Jonesport, Maine (USA). A flat at Sheep Island was constructed in 1989 and along with an adjacent reference area (REF) has been monitored for infaunal assemblage development and sediment texture since 1990. The second site, Beals Island, an example of a much older constructed flat (CF), has been monitored since 1991. Infaunal taxa richness, total numerical abundance, species composition, and diversity values were similar between the Sheep Island natural and constructed sites within two years of construction. At Beals Island, taxa richness and other diversity measures were similar between sites, however, abundance and total biomass values were lower at the constructed site. Although total biomass was also lower at the Sheep Island CF than its REF, biomass values at both constructed sites (Sheep Island and Beals Island) were within the range of values previously reported for natural flats.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="24">
	<artid>5c7a41a682cea8696b02e7edecc35895</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000795</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00079-5</doi>
	<title>Composition, Abundance and Stratification of Macrobenthos in the Marine Area Impacted by Tar Aggregates Derived from the Haven Oil Spill (Ligurian Sea, Italy) </title>
	<abstract>The impact of tar aggregates deriving from the Haven oil spill that occurred in 1991 on the soft-bottom macrobenthos off Arenzano (Ligurian Sea, NW Mediterranean; Italy) was investigated in this study. Core samples were collected to evaluate the composition, abundance and stratification of macrobenthos in three contaminated and three control sites. The distribution of tar aggregates (often settled by hydroids, bryozoans and serpulids) in the impacted area did not show distinct patterns related to sediment depth. The macrobenthos was numerically dominated by polychaetes, followed by crustaceans (amphipods, isopods and tanaids) and sipunculids, whereas bivalve molluscs were less represented. Ophiuroids and nemerteans were only occasionally found. Stratification was the main factor explaining the distribution of benthic invertebrates, highest abundances being observed in the upper 5 cm of sediment, while densities of individuals declined sharply in deeper sediment layers. No significant differences were observed in the abundance of both the whole benthic assemblage and of the main benthic taxonomic groups between contaminated and control sites. The higher abundance of sipunculids at the contaminated sites, instead, was attributed to the availability of empty tubes of polychaetes in which they take refuge. The polychaetes/amphipods ratios did not show strong differences between impacted and control sites. Multivariate analysis (MDS) showed a wide scattering among deep bottom samples and a comparatively high similarity among intermediate and superficial layers, regardless of the contamination level. In conclusion, the results reported here suggest that tar aggregates do not determine appreciable detrimental effects on the soft-bottom macrobenthos, which appeared to have recovered towards natural pristine conditions.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="25">
	<artid>943ee98cc99519467bfbea49bf175df4</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000862</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00086-2</doi>
	<title>Development and Validation of Biocriteria Using Benthic Macroinvertebrates for North Carolina Estuarine Waters </title>
	<abstract>Biological criteria were developed to assess water quality in mesohaline and polyhaline estuarine waters in North Carolina. The criteria used a combination of three metrics: a new `Hilsenhoff-type&apos; biotic index incorporating the sensitivity to pollution of each taxon and its relative abundance, total number of taxa, and number of amphipod and caridean shrimp taxa. Agreement with an independent data set was 90%, as was within site repeatability of this biocriteria over a range of water qualities and salinities. The versatility of the biotic index is discussed relative to other sampling methods and in other parts of the world.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="26">
	<artid>5f5913173490a81a09070f1c06453756</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000801</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00080-1</doi>
	<title>Heavy Metals in Eight 1965 Cores from the Novaya Zemlya Trough, Kara Sea, Russian Arctic </title>
	<abstract>The concentration and distribution of 18 chemical elements were determined in 86 samples from eight sediment cores, 89–131 cm long, collected during 1965 along a 650 km traverse in the Novaya Zemlya Trough, Kara Sea, Russian Arctic. These include potentially toxic elements followed by the Arctic monitoring and assessment program (AMAP) (e.g., As, Cr, Hg, Pb) and elements that may be related to the fine size minerals in these cores (e.g., Al, K, Mg). Arsenic and Hg had high concentrations (to 212 ppm – baseline 20 ppm, and to 875 ppb – baseline 338 ppb, respectively) in upper sections of cores. This suggests possible anthropogenic input in the Kara Sea before 1965. In contrast, most of the metals analysed had baseline contents throughout the cores. High As values in the sediments probably reflect a combination of diagenetic mobilization from depth to surface/near-surface sediments and input from human activities such as dumped military materials in the trough, mining and smelting effluents and emissions, and the burning of fossil fuel (especially coal). High Hg contents cannot be the result of the diagenetic path followed by As and may reflect an anthropogenic addition of Hg to high natural baseline values from atmospheric deposition of industrial emissions as well as from decomposition of dumped wastes (e.g., lewisite) and naval reactor coolant discharged into the sea. Arsenic and Hg discharged into the southern Kara Sea from Siberia and the Novaya Zemlya archipelago move with oceanic currents and ice-floes as suspensates or adhered particulates for deposition in the trough. Arsenic is likely mobilized in particulates as the arsenate species sorbed to ferric oxy/hydroxides whereas Hg can be mobilized in organisms as the biomethylated form or Hg species (e.g., Hg2+, HgCl42−) sorbed onto organic and/or inorganic (clay mineral) particulates. High concentrations of Mn and Mo in upper core sediments result from post-depositional mobilization from reduced deeper sediments to oxic surface sediments.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="27">
	<artid>7919bf765b954ec8de1204a183d46c4d</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000813</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00081-3</doi>
	<title>Volatile Organic Compounds in Various Marine Organisms From the Southern North Sea </title>
	<abstract>The concentration levels of 12 priority volatile organic compounds (VOCs) were determined in two species of vertebrates and four species of invertebrates from sampling stations in the southern North Sea, using a modified Tekmar LSC 2000 purge and trap system coupled to gas chromatograph–mass spectrometer (GC–MS). In general, concentration levels of VOCs found in this study were of the same order of magnitude as those previously reported in the literature. The concentrations of the chlorinated hydrocarbons (CHCs), with the exception of chloroform, tended to be lower than those of the monocyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (MAHs). The experimental data were statistically evaluated using both cluster analysis and principal component analysis (PCA). From the results of cluster analysis and PCA, no specific groups could be distinguished on the basis of geographical, temporal or biological parameters. However, based on the cluster analysis and the PCA, the VOCs could be divided into three groups, C2-substituted benzenes, CHCs and benzene plus toluene. This division could be related to different types of sources. Finally, it was shown that organisms can be used to monitor the presence of VOCs in the marine environment and the observed concentrations levels were compared with proposed safety levels.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="28">
	<artid>8e39ca128be2c70d7b87fffbbc477bf5</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000941</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00094-1</doi>
	<title>Gladstone, Australia Field Studies: Weathering and Degradation of Hydrocarbons in Oiled Mangrove and Salt Marsh Sediments With and Without the Application of an Experimental Bioremediation Protocol </title>
	<abstract>This field study was a combined chemical and biological investigation of the relative rates of weathering and biodegradation of oil spilled in sediments and testing the influence of a bioremediation protocol. The aim of the chemistry work presented here was to determine whether the bioremediation protocol affected the rate of penetration, dissipation or long-term retention of a medium range crude oil (Gippsland) and a Bunker C oil stranded in tropical Rhizophora sp. mangrove and Halosarcia sp. salt marsh environments. Permission for the planned oil spills was granted in the Port Authority area of Gladstone, Queensland (Australia). Sediment cores from three replicate plots of each treatment for mangroves and four replicate plots for the salt marsh (oil only and oil plus bioremediation) were analysed for total hydrocarbons (THC) and for individual alkane markers using gas chromatography with flame ionization detection (GC–FID). Sediments were collected at day 2, then 1, 2, 5 or 6 and 12 or 13 months post-spill for mangroves and day 2, 1, 3 and 9 months post-spill for salt marshes. Over this time, hydrocarbons in all of the oil treated plots decreased exponentially. There was no statistical difference in initial oil concentrations, penetration of oil to depth, or in the rates of oil dissipation between untreated oil and bioremediated oil in the mangrove plots. The salt marsh plots treated with the waxy Gippsland oil showed a faster rate of biodegradation of the oil in the bioremediated plots. In this case only, the degradation rate significantly impacted the mass balance of remaining oil. The Bunker C oil contained only minor amounts of highly degradable n-alkanes and bioremediation did not significantly impact its rate of loss in the salt marsh sediments. At the end of each experiment, there were still n-alkanes visible in the gas chromatograms of residual oils. Thus it was concluded that there was unlikely to be any change in the stable internal biomarkers of the oils over this time period. The predominant removal processes in both habitats were evaporation and dissolution, with a lag-phase of 1–2 months before the start of microbial degradation.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="29">
	<artid>c5d74a129f4497a31cde9f0d3705f852</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000928</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00092-8</doi>
	<title>Composition, Distribution and Sources of Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons in Sediments of the Gulf of Trieste, Northern Adriatic Sea </title>
	<abstract>The composition, distribution and the sources of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) in the surficial sediments of the Gulf of Trieste were investigated. To document the spatial PAH input, surficial sediment samples from 17 locations throughout the Gulf were analysed. The total PAH load determined in the surficial sediment samples are between 30 and 600 ng g−1, and were the highest in the immediate vicinity of the Port of Trieste. The PAH contents decline rapidly with increasing distance from the shore. The ratios of methylphenanthrenes/phenanthrene and methylpyrene/pyrene are sensitive indicators of the origin of PAH pollution in the Gulf which is mostly pyrolitic. The phenanthrene/anthracene ratio was used to determine the approximate location and distance from the source of PAH pollution, while 1-methy l-7-isopropylphenanthrene (retene) was used as indicator for forest fires. A sediment depth profile indicates a major increase in the PAH concentrations after the First World War.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="30">
	<artid>af03419581d7bc09ac364b1f236e4661</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X0000093X</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00093-X</doi>
	<title>Evidence for Systemic Changes in the Benthic Fauna of Tropical Estuaries as a Result of Urbanization </title>
	<abstract>The effects of urban development cause substantial physical changes in coastal waterways through hardening and reclamation of river banks, alteration of water flow, and diffuse and point-source discharges of pollutants. The cumulative effects of urbanization on the fauna of estuaries are not well understood. This study examined the benthic infauna of two urban and three rural estuaries near Townsville, North Queensland. A range of univariate and multivariate statistics was used to relate variation in the benthic assemblages to concentrations of contaminants (heavy metals and hydrocarbons) within the sediments of each estuary. Sediments in the most developed estuary contained concentrations of heavy metals and petroleum hydrocarbons that were several orders of magnitude greater than those from non-urban waterways. The fauna at these sites was dominated by cirratulid and sternaspid polychaetes and lacked filter-feeding bivalves and other molluscs that were common in less developed estuaries. These differences were generally consistent throughout each estuary, indicating estuary-wide patterns of change, that were most strongly associated with spatial patterns in the distribution of Pb, Cu and hydrocarbons.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="31">
	<artid>12081f392a82a90c195b0ce738100872</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000874</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00087-4</doi>
	<title>Clostridium perfringens as a Potential Indicator for the Presence of Sewage Solids in Marine Sediments </title>
	<abstract>Marine sediment cores collected from several depths of water and distances from a California sewage outfall were tested to see if sediments influenced by sewage solids were a reservoir of enteric pathogens, and if concentrations of indicator bacteria were related to the presence of sewage solids. Vertical distributions of microorganisms in marine sediments were determined; there was a decrease of indicator bacteria with increasing sediment depth. Aeromonas was randomly isolated, but none of the enteric bacterial pathogens or viruses were detected. While classic indicator bacteria were of little value in predicting the presence of pathogens, or relative amounts of sewage solids, Clostridium perfringens may be a suitable indicator. Clostridium perfringens concentrations were not related to the presence of pathogens in sediments.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="32">
	<artid>c200caeba3e43f0d55b9312472e456a1</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000953</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00095-3</doi>
	<title>Pesticides in Sediments From Queensland Irrigation Channels and Drains </title>
	<abstract>Pesticide concentration in sediment from irrigation areas can provide information required to assess exposure and fate of these chemicals in freshwater ecosystems and their likely impacts to the marine environment. In this study, 103 sediment samples collected from irrigation channels and drains in 11 agricultural areas of Queensland were analysed for a series of past and presently used pesticides including various organochlorines, synthetic pyrethroids, benzoyl ureas, triazines and organophosphates. The most often detected compounds were endosulphans (α, β and/or endosulphan sulphate) which were detectable in 78 of the 103 samples and levels ranged from below the limit of quantification (0.1 ng g−1 dw) up to 840 ng g−1 dw. DDT and its metabolites were the second most often detected pesticide investigated (74 of the 103 samples) with concentrations up to 240 ng g−1 dw of ∑DDTs. Mean ∑endosulphan and ∑DDT concentrations were 1–2 orders of magnitude higher in sediments from the irrigation areas which are dominated by cotton cultivation compared to those which are dominated by sugarcane cultivation. In contrast to these insecticides, the herbicides diuron, atrazine and ametryn were the compounds which were most often detected in sediments from irrigation drains in sugarcane areas with maximum concentrations in areas of 120, 70 and 130 ng g−1 dw, respectively. In particular during flood events, when light is limiting, transport of these photosynthesis inhibiting herbicides from the sugarcane cultivation areas to the marine environment may result in additional stress of marine plants.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="33">
	<artid>5f7710aed58399408fd51b1e547a4ac5</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000965</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00096-5</doi>
	<title>Research, Extension and Industry – Working Together Can Achieve Results </title>
	<abstract>Over recent decades, research has been directed to assessing the impacts of land uses on valuable natural assets, such as the Great Barrier Reef. Land managers in adjacent areas are expected to adopt practices to minimize any adverse affects on downstream environments. Conversely, researchers are being pressed to provide answers to the problems. In response, researchers and environmental managers are bombarding land managers with information regarding the potential environmental implications of their practices. Is this an effective mode to achieve on-ground change?Collaboration between all groups – research, industry and extension – may be more effective in developing and implementing practical solutions to these more complex issues. A change from the research and extension models currently used may be needed to achieve positive resource management outcomes.Research, development and extension initiatives underway in the Australian sugar industry to improve farm practice and reduce the potential for adverse impacts on downstream environments are discussed. Case studies provide some insights into how science and extension skills work best together and how an industry group can respond to a community concern.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="34">
	<artid>428837f81bc4568091b826a2972d7ae4</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001028</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00102-8</doi>
	<title>North and South Carolina Coasts </title>
	<abstract>This coastal region of North and South Carolina is a gently sloping plain, containing large riverine estuaries, sounds, lagoons, and salt marshes. The most striking feature is the large, enclosed sound known as the Albemarle–Pamlico Estuarine System, covering approximately 7530 km2. The coast also has numerous tidal creek estuaries ranging from 1 to 10 km in length. This coast has a rapidly growing population and greatly increasing point and non-point sources of pollution. Agriculture is important to the region, swine rearing notably increasing fourfold during the 1990s.Estuarine phytoplankton communities in North Carolina are well studied; the most important taxonomic groups are diatoms, dinoflagellates, cryptomonads and cyanobacteria. Several major poorly flushed estuaries are eutrophic due to nutrient inputs, and toxic dinoflagellates (Pfiesteria spp) can reach high densities in nutrient-enriched areas. Fully marine waters are relatively oligotrophic. Southern species enter in subsurface intrusions, eddies, and occasional Gulf Stream rings, while cool water species enter with the flow of the Labrador Current to the Cape Hatteras region. The Carolinas have a low number of endemic macroalgae, but species diversity can be high in this transitional area, which represents the southernmost extension for some cold-adapted species and the northernmost extension of warm-adapted species. In North Carolina the dominant seagrass, Zostera marina, lies at its southernmost extension, while a second species, Halodule wrightii is at its northernmost extent. Widgeon-grass Ruppia maritima is common, growing in brackish water or low-salinity pools in salt marshes. Seagrass meadows are now much reduced, probably due to elevated nitrogen and increased sedimentation.In sounds, numerically dominant benthic taxa include bivalves, polychaetes and amphipods, many showing gradients in community type from mesohaline areas of the eastern shore to near marine salinities in western parts. The semi-enclosed sounds have extensive shellfisheries, especially of blue crab, northern quahogs, eastern oysters, and shrimp. Problems include contamination of some sediments with toxic substances, especially of metals and PCBs at sufficiently high levels to depress growth of some benthic macroinvertebrates. Numerous fish kills have been caused by toxic Pfiesteria outbreaks, and fish kills and habitat loss have been caused by episodic hypoxia and anoxia in rivers and estuaries. Oyster beds currently are in decline because of overharvesting, high siltation and suspended particulate loads, disease, hypoxia, and coastal development. Fisheries monitoring which began in the late 1970s shows greatest recorded landings in 1978–1982; since then, harvests have declined by about a half.Some management plans have been developed toward improving water quality and fisheries sustainability. Major challenges include; high coliform levels leading to closures of shellfish beds, a problem that has increased with urban development and increasing cover of watershed by impervious surfaces; high by-catch and heavy trawling activity; overfishing which has led to serious declines in many wild fish stocks; and eutrophication. Comprehensive plans limiting nutrient inputs are needed for all coastal rivers and estuaries, not only those that already exhibit problems. There is a critical need to improve management of non-point nutrient runoff through increased use of streamside vegetated buffers, preservation of remaining natural wetlands and construction of artificial wetlands. Improved treatment processes, based on strong incentive programmes, should also be mandated for present and future industrial-scale animal operations.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="35">
	<artid>2b738ec0e34457f1b78d1503acba2837</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000977</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00097-7</doi>
	<title>Pesticide and Herbicide Residues in Sediments and Seagrasses from the Great Barrier Reef World Heritage Area and Queensland Coast </title>
	<abstract>Pesticides and herbicides including organochlorine compounds have had extensive current and past application by Queensland&apos;s intensive coastal agriculture industry as well as for a wide range of domestic, public health and agricultural purposes in urban areas. The persistent nature of these types of compounds together with possible continued illegal use of banned organochlorine compounds raises the potential for continued long-term chronic exposure to plants and animals of the Great Barrier Reef. Sediment and seagrass samples were collected from 16 intertidal and 25 subtidal sampling sites between Torres Strait and Townsville, near Mackay and Gladstone, and in Hervey and Moreton Bays in 1997 and 1998 and analysed for pesticide and herbicide residues. Low levels of atrazine (0.1–0.3 μg kg−1), diuron (0.2–10.1 μg kg−1), lindane (0.08–0.19 μg kg−1), dieldrin (0.05–0.37 μg kg−1), DDT (0.05–0.26 μg kg−1), and DDE (0.05–0.26 μg kg−1) were detected in sediments and/or seagrasses. Contaminants were mainly detected in samples collected along the high rainfall, tropical coast between Townsville and Port Douglas and in Moreton Bay. Of the contaminants detected, the herbicide diuron is of most concern as the concentrations detected have some potential to impact local seagrass communities.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="36">
	<artid>8543d20e0d8fee10417e773d71091644</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001041</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00104-1</doi>
	<title>The Bahamas </title>
	<abstract>The archipelago of the Bahamas contains the largest tropical shallow water area in the Western Atlantic. Located on the northern and eastern margins of two large submerged banks and a number of smaller more isolated banks, the Bahama Islands, of which there are over 700, are low-lying and composed of limestone. A sub-tropical climate and a geographic position between two major warm ocean currents affect the region with seasonal variability, which influences the biological communities inhabiting the ocean and coastal areas.The Bahama Banks are separated from the North American continent by the Florida Straits and from each other by deep channels, some in excess of 2000 m. Two deep water channels cut into the larger Great Bahama Bank. Most of the marine area is shallow (≪20 m), resulting in an extremely important marine resource with both ecological and economic value.The Bahama Islands are dependent on their seas to maintain a GDP of US$ 2.7 billion through tourism and harvest of marine resources. To date, the fishing industry has benefited from the relatively high ecological productivity of the shallow banks and their related habitats. Commercially important fisheries include Spiny Lobster, conch and nassau grouper which, together, make up the bulk of fisheries income.Clear warm waters and white sand beaches, along with its close proximity to the USA, make the Bahamas a prime tourist destination. Tourism is the mainstay of the Bahamian economy, accounting for 60% of the gross domestic product.Agricultural and forestry operations are limited and impacts in the coastal zone from these are negligible. However, land reclamation and construction for tourism development, along with sand mining, dredging, over-fishing, poor fishing practices and their respective impacts of habitat loss, beach erosion and over-exploitation of target and non-target marine resources are becoming increasingly apparent as developmental pressures grow.Environmental regulations are in place through a number of parliamentary acts. Management of established marine and coastal protected areas has been undertaken by the Bahamas National Trust (BNT), which along with other organisations, carry out environmental education programs to increase awareness and reduce impact on the marine and coastal areas of the archipelago.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="37">
	<artid>9f72880defa417e6f362cfe48b2c4946</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00000990</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00099-0</doi>
	<title>The North Sea </title>
	<abstract>The North Sea is a semi-enclosed, epi-continental large marine ecosystem (LME) in northern Europe. It is relatively shallow (average depth 90 m), extending north to the Norwegian Trench (700 m); the climate is temperate. Because of highly developed industry and agriculture in its watershed, pollution from contaminants and nutrients has been a major environmental issue for decades. Atmospheric inputs of contaminants are also important. Fisheries, and the protection of species and habitats, have become major concerns, and legislation is still developing to address threats to biological diversity, especially of coastal areas which are under pressure from numerous activities. The regulatory framework for the management of the North Sea is constantly changing. The 1992 ‘Paris Convention’ came into force under the auspices of the Oslo and Paris Commissions (OSPARCOM) in 1998. With the increasing influence of the European Union, there is considerable overlap between the EU and OSPAR, leading to duplication between these and other organizations such as the International Conferences for the Protection of the North Sea and the International Council for the Exploration of the Sea. Although a great deal of scientific research has been carried out in this region, the need for additional data is still a crucial precursor to management.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="38">
	<artid>0ea38dbc7f7258d2bb3ad32f32a239c0</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001120</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00112-0</doi>
	<title>Particle Dry Deposition to Water Surfaces: Processes and Consequences </title>
	<abstract>Algal blooms (increased abundance of phytoplankton) are an increasingly common phenomenon which has been causally linked to increased fluxes of nutrient (particularly nitrogenous) compounds to aquatic ecosystems. These blooms have implications for water quality and human health in addition to ecosystem productivity, health and ecological diversity. Anthropogenic emissions of nitrogen to the atmosphere are estimated to be comparable to, or greater than, biogenic emissions but are considerably more concentrated in space. Although fluvial pathways typically dominate the annually averaged nitrogen flux to coastal waters, atmosphere–surface exchange represents a significant component of the total flux and may be particularly critical during the summertime when both the riverine input and ambient nutrient concentrations are often at a minimum. In this chapter, we present an overview of the physical and chemical processes which dictate the quantity (and direction) of atmosphere–surface fluxes of trace chemicals to (and above) water surfaces with particular emphasis on the role of particles.Dry deposition (transfer to the surface in the absence of precipitation) of particles is determined by meteorological conditions, atmospheric concentrations, surface type/condition and the specific chemical and physical properties of the particle. Dry deposition can be conceptualized as a three-step process: (1) the gas or particle is moved toward the surface by thermally or mechanically driven eddies; (2) it is transferred by diffusion across a thin layer close to the surface where turbulence is absent; and (3) the gas or particle is captured by the surface. In the case of larger particles a second parallel pathway exists; particles are drawn towards the surface by gravity. Atmospheric particles determine dry deposition fluxes not only by serving as a conduit for transfer but also because of their action as sources or sinks of trace gases. The example given here is the transfer of nitric acid to sea salt particles as a result of heterogeneous chemistry acting as a competing sink to surface removal. To illustrate the importance of current uncertainties in our understanding of dry deposition processes and to highlight the role of some of the key parameters in determining the transfer rate (the deposition velocity) a simple model of particle dry deposition is presented. The model describes the calculation of the rate at which a particle of a given size and chemical composition will be moved towards the surface under given environmental conditions. Observational and experimental techniques for measuring dry deposition fluxes are also reviewed. The techniques used for gases are largely reliant on use of highly temporally resolved sampling (e.g., concentrations sampled 10 times per second) or highly accurate and precise measurements of concentrations, either in the vertical to resolve the gradient to or from the surface or conditionally sampled by the direction of transfer (to or from the surface). These stringent measurement requirements represent significant barriers to application to measurement of particle dry deposition fluxes although, as discussed, innovative solutions are now becoming available.In the final section, we examine meteorological controls on deposition to the coastal zone. This region of the world’s oceans and seas is most significantly impacted by human activities. More than half of the world’s population lives within 100 km of a coast and hence the overwhelming majority of anthropogenic fluxes to aquatic systems occur in the coastal zone. We discuss the particular challenges that arise from efforts to simulate and measure fluxes close to the coastline. These arise in part from the complexity of atmospheric flow in this region where energy and chemical fluxes are highly inhomogeneous in space and time and thermally generated atmospheric circulations are commonplace.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="39">
	<artid>3b702d1085c1e878d046a93674736cf0</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001077</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00107-7</doi>
	<title>The Indian Ocean Coast of Somalia </title>
	<abstract>Somalia has the longest national coastline (3025 km) in Africa with an estimated shelf area (depth 0–200 m) of 32 500 km2. The country is divided into the northern coastal plain of Guban, which has a semi-arid terrain; the northern highlands with rugged mountain ranges containing the country’s highest peak (2407 m); and the Ogaden region which descends to the south from the highlands and which consists of shallow plateau valleys, wadis and broken mountains. The latter region continues to the Mudug plain in central Somalia.From Ras Caseyr to the Kenya border, the coast runs north-east to south-west, coinciding with the displacement caused by the Mesozoic marginal subsidence. This general structure is complicated by sedimentary troughs crossing the Horn of Africa, and by large sedimentary basins, cutting the coastline and extending inland into Southern Somalia and Northern Kenya (Juba–Lamu embayment, Mogadishu basin). Offshore, the western Somali Basin extends from Socotra to the Comores. The open shelf environments developed along the Somali coast are a consequence of an extensive marine transgression, connected to coastal subsidence or inland uplift.The rocks along the southern coastal belt are Pliocene–Pleistocene, and are characterized by a sequence of both marine and continental deposits of skeletal sands, coral build-ups, eolian sands and paleosols. As well as eolian and biogenic sedimentary processes, sea-level fluctuations, Holocene climatic changes and neotectonic movements have combined to produce the modern coastline. A notable feature is an ancient dune ridge complex, known as the Merka red dune, which rims the coast extending beyond the Kenyan border and which separates the narrow coastal belt from the Uebi Shebeli alluvial plain. Two features of note are the Bajuni Archipelago, which consists of islands, islets and skerries, forming a barrier island separated from the coast by a narrow marine sound, and a braided, channelized coastal area, which originated from the drowning of a paleofluvial net.The southern Somali coast, with that of Kenya and Tanzania, forms part of the Somali Current Large Marine Ecosystem, encompassing 700 000 km2, and extending 800 km between Dar es Salaam and Ras Hafun. Abundant biomass develops here due to upwelling. The shelf area has a wide variety of coral reefs, mangroves, seagrass meadows, beaches and estuaries. In shallow water areas the abraded flats are colonized by scattered coral communities with variable cover. A true fringing reef is achieved in places only in the Bajuni archipelago. All along the southern Somali coastal shelf there are spreading meadows of Thalassodendron seagrass, and benthic communities typical of mobile sandy substrates are limited to beach ridges and shoals developed along the coastline. Around the Bajuni barrier island and the channelized area there is more diversity. Mangroves grow on the tidal belts of the channels, and there are expanses of salt flats.Large-scale alteration produced by man on the Somali coast is relatively recent, but has accelerated in the last few decades, especially around major cities. This alteration affects especially backshore areas where the Pleistocene coral reefs are quarried. At present, the continental shelf is not adequately monitored or protected, so coastal habitats are being degraded, living marine resources are overexploited, and pollution levels are increasing, all of which affect natural resources and biodiversity.Somalia is one of the world’s poorest and least developed countries, with few resources and devastated by civil war, but since 1993 it has been part of the Common Market for Eastern and Southern Africa (COMESA). This will affect fisheries and aquaculture in terms of the investment, production, trade and fish consumption of the member states. There are currently no marine protected areas and no legislation concerning their establishment and management, although the World Conservation Monitoring Centre (WCMC) Protected Areas Database lists Busc Busc Game Reserve as an MPA. In 1992, The WCMC also listed the following coastal sites as proposed protected areas: Zeila (important sea bird colonies on offshore islets), Jowhar–Warshek, Awdhegle–Gandershe. The area from Kisimayo to Ras Chiambone is probably of highest priority, as it is important for coral reefs, marine turtles, and mangrove resources, although it is still poorly known.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="40">
	<artid>e68db8f69f4a3e16ff4d7fc05cc7cba6</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001089</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00108-9</doi>
	<title>The Malacca Straits </title>
	<abstract>The Malacca Straits have long been an important trade route linking the Indian Ocean to the South China Sea and Pacific Ocean. From the seventh to the eleventh century, the Srivijaya empire controlled them, followed in the fifteenth century by the port kingdom of Malacca. Western maritime powers also recognized the strategic importance of the Straits, and in 1511, the Portuguese captured Malacca. In 1641, the Dutch occupied what is now known as Jakarta, and from the seventeenth to the eighteenth century, the Dutch East India company controlled the trade in the Straits (Ross et al., 1995). The British also recognized the need to control the Straits to ensure the safe passage of British merchant ships on their way to China, and in 1819 established a colony in Singapore. In 1824, the British and the Dutch ended their rivalry with a treaty whereby Britain agreed to `safeguard the Straits and keep them open for other friendly nations&apos; (Chia, 1998).In recent years, the Straits have become a very important trade route. In 1993 and 1995, over 100 000 oil and cargo vessels traversed it each year, carrying 3.23 million barrels of crude oil through the Straits each day (Sakura Institute of Research, 1998). Shipping accidents have occurred more frequently, recently, which is attributed to heavy traffic in the Straits with shallow, narrow channels and shoals. Despite these hazards, economic efficiency dictates that vessels continue to use the Straits.The Straits are also rich in renewable and non-renewable resources, including productive coastal ecosystems, extensive capture fisheries, aquaculture, coastal tourism, mining and valuable natural gas reserves.This chapter looks at the natural environmental conditions and the status of the coastal resources, the sustainability of existing activities, critical environmental problems and management. It is based on the Malacca Straits Environmental Profile (Chua et al., 1997) and other studies undertaken by the GEF/UNDP/IMO Regional Programme for Marine Pollution Prevention and Management in the East Asian Seas, referred to as the Regional Programme in this document.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="41">
	<artid>b56afcee05bc7da0d865a7f78852ae73</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001119</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00111-9</doi>
	<title>By-Catch: Problems and Solutions </title>
	<abstract>By-catch is one of the most significant issues affecting fisheries management today. Incidental mortality of species which are long-lived and have low reproductive rates is a conservation problem affecting marine mammals, sea birds, sea turtles, sharks and other groups. By-catches can affect biodiversity through impacts on top predators, the removal of individuals from many species, or by elimination of prey. The by-catch issue is also one of waste; the millions of tons of protein dumped in the ocean, and the waste of animal lives is often condemned on moral grounds. For the economist, it generates additional costs without affecting the revenues, and may hinder profitability. For the fishers, it causes conflicts among fisheries, it gives fishers a bad public image, generates regulations and limitations on the use of resources, and frequently has negative effects on the resources harvested through the mortality of juvenile and undersized individuals of the target species before they reach their optimal size from the point of view of future yield.Several examples of major by-catch issues are described, focusing also on the solutions to the problems which have been developed by scientists, fisheries managers and members of the fishing industry itself. By-catch is an extremely complex set of scientific issues, not only an economic, political, or moral one. Although only a few fisheries include by-catches of the target species in their stock assessment (e.g. Pacific halibut), it is clear that by-catch management will be an integral part of most future ecosystem management schemes. These considerations, together with the introduction of environmental variability and a better handling of scientific uncertainty, should lead to more intelligent ways to harvest our resources.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="42">
	<artid>755458ff35572dad6fed940a1a75cf5d</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001107</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00110-7</doi>
	<title>The Eastern Australian Region: a Dynamic Tropical/Temperate Biotone </title>
	<abstract>Eastern Australia lies in an overlap of tropical Indo-Pacific and temperate bioregions because of the influence of the southward-flowing East Australian Current. It has a very high biodiversity, from tropical coral reef and seagrass in the north, to coastal lakes and kelp communities in the south. Offshore, Norfolk and Lord Howe Islands and Elizabeth and Middleton Reefs, are the highest latitude coral reefs in the world. The coastal region includes South-East Queensland and New South Wales (NSW) and supports almost half of Australia’s population. Catchments have been extensively cleared for agriculture and water quality in many rivers and estuaries is poor. There has been major loss of wetlands and acid soil runoff causes fish kills and diseases in estuaries. The coastline is exposed, and much has been mined for heavy minerals and is subject to erosion. Urbanization and industrialization, particularly in the Sydney area, has resulted in sewage and heavy metal pollution. Many of the coastal fisheries are declining, largely because of loss of water quality and wetlands habitats, and in some cases overfishing. Marine environmental management (the responsibility of the two states to the 3 mile limit, and the Commonwealth to the boundary of the 200 mile EEZ) is variable, and largely focused on the urban centres. Queensland has a system of marine protected areas (MPAs) while NSW has minimal protected areas. The major issues are declining water quality, loss of estuarine habitats, degradation of coastal lakes, and localized pollution from heavy metals and sewage in the Sydney area.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="43">
	<artid>b53b8b33381e3f162ef4055da3c42277</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001132</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00113-2</doi>
	<title>Marine Ecosystem Health as an Expression of Morbidity, Mortality and Disease Events </title>
	<abstract>Over the last 50 years, national, international and private stewardship and conservation organizations have spent billions of dollars collecting marine ecosystem information. This remains divided among many custodians, scattered among thousands of published sources and, from a global perspective, is fragmentary in nature. It is argued that new resource management questions regarding coastal ecosystem health can be addressed through the recovery and `data mining&apos; of this previously collected and often discarded information. A retrospective marine epidemiological approach was developed to demonstrate that marine morbidity, mortality, and disease information is recoverable by keyword searching of academic journals and through the retrieval of publicly available digital and print-media information. Observational records compiled from disturbances occurring within the Northwestern Atlantic, Gulf of Mexico, and Caribbean Sea confirm that anomalous marine morbidity and mortality events have increased in number and frequency during the last 30 years. A global approach is summarized for systematically reconstructing spatial and temporal disturbance indicator time series using data mining and data reduction techniques.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="44">
	<artid>b83cb46d58966a64de95fc85164c8d83</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001144</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00114-4</doi>
	<title>Eutrophication of Marine Waters: Effects on Benthic Microbial Communities </title>
	<abstract>During the last century organic pollution in coastal areas of the sea has become a serious world problem. One of the major stresses comes from the input of excessive macronutrients (nitrogen, phosphorus) resulting in a change of the trophic status of a given body of water, which leads to eutrophication. Although the effects of eutrophication are well-known, the mechanisms governing its effects are poorly understood. In particular, effects on microbial processes are key to many aspects of the functioning of the ecosystem, and commonly are inadequately addressed. The effects of eutrophication on benthic microbial communities are demonstrated using shallow-water coastal inlets in the southern Baltic Sea as an example. These so-called `Bodden&apos; are characterized by pronounced gradients of inorganic and organic nutrients. For the hypertrophic innermost parts of the Bodden, critical points can be identified at which the chronic stress caused by eutrophication could no longer be compensated for by the system. Signs of eutrophication of sediments of the Bodden include increases in inorganic and organic carbon, nitrogen and phosphorus, microbial biomass and enzymatic decomposition potential of substrates, nitrification, denitrification, and nutrient fluxes from the sediments, all of which can be measured. Above certain carbon concentrations, further increases in organic carbon are not necessarily paralleled by corresponding increases in biological parameters. This might be taken as an indication of a different status of nutrient enrichment. Eutrophication effects became most obvious from changes in the ratios of pelagic to benthic primary production, oxygen to sulphate respiration, and proteolytic to carbohydrate decomposing enzyme activities. The structure and function of microbial biofilms colonizing stones and sediments also reflected the changed trophic status. With increasing eutrophication, the ratio of autotrophic to heterotrophic microbial processes becomes greatly reduced. Drifting filamentous macroalgae, mats of sulphur oxidizing and anaerobic phototrophic bacteria, represent visible signs of eutrophication. Although the external nutrient loads in the example of the Bodden have been greatly reduced during the last decade, the internal loads of the sediments remain a serious problem. Remediation concepts can only support the natural self-purification potential of a marine coastal ecosystem.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="45">
	<artid>1c598574f419f9c34ff7dec5aabf48a6</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001156</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00115-6</doi>
	<title>Holistic Environmental Assessment and Offshore Oil Field Exploration and Production </title>
	<abstract>According to UK Government surveys, concern for the environment is growing. Environmental regulation of the industry is becoming wider in its scope and tougher in its implementation. Various techniques are available to assess how the industry can drive down its environmental impact and comply with environmental regulation. Environmental Assessments (EA) required by European law do not cover the whole life cycle of the project that they are analysing. Life Cycle Analysis (LCA) was developed to assess the environmental loadings of a product, process or activity over its entire life cycle. It was the first technique used in environmental analysis that adopted what was described as a holistic approach. It fails this approach by not assessing accidental emissions or environmental impacts other than those that are direct. Cost Benefit Analysis (CBA) offers the opportunity to value environmental effects and appraise a project on the basis of costs and benefits. Not all environmental effects can be valued and of those that can there is considerable uncertainty in their valuation and occurrence. CBA cannot satisfactorily measure the total environmental risk of a project. Consequently there is a need for a technique that overcomes the failures of project-level EA, LCA and CBA, and assesses total environmental risk. Many organizations such as, the British Medical Association, the European Oilfield Speciality Chemicals Association, the Royal Ministry of Petroleum and Energy (Norway) and Shell Expro now recognize that a holistic approach is an integral part of assessing total risk. The Brent SPAR case study highlights the interdisciplinary nature required of any environmental analysis. Holistic Environmental Assessment is recommended as such an environmental analysis.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="46">
	<artid>805e302fe1720865cc2e31a612abdc61</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X0000120X</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00120-X</doi>
	<title>Evidence for the Effects of Metal Contamination on the Intertidal Macrobenthic Assemblages of the Fal Estuary </title>
	<abstract>The intertidal invertebrate macrofauna of five creeks in the Fal estuarine system, Cornwall, UK, is compared with data from 40 locations in six other estuaries in south-west Britain. Multivariate analysis shows that the community composition in the Fal is distinct from all the other estuaries. The differences are principally due to the absence of two crustacean species, Corophium volutator and Cyathura carinata, and the high abundance of small opportunistic annelid species. The Fal Estuary is heavily contaminated with heavy metals as a result of mining in the catchment, and the faunistic features are commensurate with what is known of the relative sensitivities of marine invertebrate taxa to pollution.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="47">
	<artid>8824b68a73a2270a49e7c47dbd548651</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001223</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00122-3</doi>
	<title>Box Coring Artifacts in Sediments Affected by a Waste Water Outfall </title>
	<abstract>Variations in porosity of surface sediments are often the major cause of sediment loss during gravity and box coring. Sediments with a high content of organic matter usually have higher porosity, and thus, lower resistance (strain) towards mechanical disturbance. Here, we demonstrate that box coring artifacts (i.e. sediment loss and core shortening) can be produced in sediments from the Palos Verdes (PV) shelf, which in the past had received relatively high loads of organic carbon (OC) enriched particulate matter originating from the Whites Point outfall that had created a high porosity layer at depth. This has been overlooked as a possibility for obtaining low estimates of sediment and pollutant accumulation rates. Since any such sediment loss during coring can lead to serious underestimates of sedimentation rates, our results here may have important implications for any attempts at reconstructing pollutant fluxes and histories in these coastal marine sediments.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="48">
	<artid>ad2c8fa53317c1026f16327c0f4e0ddd</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001181</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00118-1</doi>
	<title>DDT, PAH and PCB in Sediments from the Intertidal Zone of the Bohai Sea and the Yellow Sea </title>
	<abstract>Current contents of persistent organic contaminants, polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs), polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons (PAHs) and the congeners (naphthalene, fluorene, phenanthrene, anthracene, fluoranthene, pyrene, chrysene, benzo(a)anthracene, benzo(a)pyrene and benzo(e)pyrene), DDTs and metabolites in the intertidal sediments of the Bohai Sea and the Yellow Sea were studied. The mean levels of DDTs, PAHs and PCBs were 177.52, 877.2 and 3.4 &lt;1 K)&quot; title=&quot;Full-size image (&lt;1 K)&quot; src=&quot;/sd/grey_pxl.gif&quot; data-inlimgeid=&quot;1-s2.0-S0025326X00001181-si2.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;1 K)&quot; title=&quot;Full-size image (&lt;1 K)&quot; src=&quot;http://origin-ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S0025326X00001181-si2.gif&quot;&gt; dry weight, respectively. The spatial trends of the contaminant residue levels were analysed too.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="49">
	<artid>df6ff8b94eff892715cfc0ec6e9d5f65</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001168</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00116-8</doi>
	<title>Changes in Macroalgal Communities in the Vicinity of a Mediterranean Sewage Outfall After the Setting Up of a Treatment Plant </title>
	<abstract>Benthic macroalgal communities of the upper rocky sublittoral were studied in 1995–1996 in the vicinity of the Marseille (Mediterranean, France) sewage outfall, 8 years after the setting up of a wastewater treatment plant and compared to a previous study carried out in 1972–1974. The number of taxa has increased, a clear stational and seasonal gradient of differentiation of the vegetation appeared, and a turf of ephemeral species is taking place of Corallina elongata at sites close to the outfall. These changes may be due to a decrease in pollutant load, the discharge of ferric chlorates used in the treatment process. However, the overall change is much less conspicuous than that described for deeper soft bottom communities, in particular the Cystoseira amantacea community is not still restored. Biological traits of this species (short distance dispersal) and the nature of most pollutants removed from the effluent (solids and organic matter) may explain this phenomenon.</abstract>
</article>
<article ocid="50">
	<artid>452ad3118c1fae7b9a516092a76de818</artid>
	<url>http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0025326X00001284</url>
	<doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0025-326X(00)00128-4</doi>
	<title>Indicator Tissues for Heavy Metal Monitoring – Additional Attributes </title>
	<abstract>Preferred characteristics of biological indicators for heavy metal monitoring in marine ecosystems were documented 30 years ago. Heavy metal data from Raine Island on the outer-northern Great Barrier Reef are presented to introduce additional attributes for consideration, including a widened choice of biological tissues due to advances in trace heavy metal analysis. Kidney tissues, visceral mass and adductor muscle from the giant clam (Tridacna maxima), muscle tissue from trochus (Trochus niloticus) and axial muscle from four species of fish were targeted. The kidneys of giant clams had concentrations of heavy metals from 2 (Zn) to 2780 (Ni) times higher than corresponding concentrations in adductor muscles. Also, tissues of giant clam and the muscle of trochus gave different signals with respect to bio-available heavy metals. Linear correlations for heavy metals within and between tissues of giant clam and within muscle tissue of trochus, offer opportunities for the use of surrogates as well as a possible mathematical basis for assessing trends in heavy metal pollution.</abstract>
</article>
</elsevier>